Finding Aid for Earl F. Dodge papers, 1906 and 1939-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Earl F. Dodge papers 1906, 1939-2004
Dodge, Earl Farwell, 1932-
4 linear feet
851097 Aa 2
National Prohibition Party official and president of the Good Government Association of Kalamazoo, Michigan. Correspondence, newspaper clippings, and other papers concerning the Prohibition Party and Good Government Association, including materials relating to his interest in politics and civic issues.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from Earl F. Dodge (donor no. 4784 ) and from the Good Government Association of Kalamazoo (donor no. 4792 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Earl Farwell Dodge Jr. was born in Revere, Massachusetts on December 24, 1932. From an early age, he was active in the affairs of the Prohibition Party assuming increasingly responsible positions. He was secretary of the party from 1957 to 1963 and from 1967 to 1979. In 1979, Dodge was appointed chairman of the party. He ran for office many times but was never elected. He was his party's candidate for vice president in 1976 and 1980.
Dodge moved to Kalamazoo, Michigan in the 1960s, where in addition to his party responsibilities he was also involved in the Kalamazoo Community Relations Boards and the Kalamazoo Good Government Association. He moved to Colorado in the early 1970s remaining engaged in the temperance and right-to-life movements. He died in December 2007.
The Earl F. Dodge collection is comprised of three series: Correspondence and other mailings; Prohibition Party activities; and Other Civic and Church activities. The collection only covers the period up to the time Dodge left for Colorado around 1972. Most heavily documented are Prohibition Party campaigns and Dodge's activities in Kalamazoo, Michigan. Among his correspondents were Rutherford L. Decker, Delmar D. Gibbons, Billy Graham, Wilbur E. Hammaker, E. Harold Munn, Thruston B. Morton, Richard M. Nixon and Mark R. Shaw.
Subjects:
Conservatism.; Elections--United States--1960.; Elections--United States--1962.; Elections--United States--1966.; Good Government Association (Kalamazoo, Mich.); Kalamazoo (Mich.); Prohibition--United States.; Prohibition Party (Mass.); Prohibition Party (Mich.); Prohibition National Committee (U.S.); Temperance--United States.; United States--Congress--Elections--1966.; United States--Politics and government--1961-1963.; United States--Politics and government--1963-1969.; United States--Politics and government--1953-1961.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
International Reform Federation, inc.; Prohibition Party (U.S.)
Contributors:
Decker, Rutherford L.; Gibbons, Delmar D., 1913-; Graham, Billy, 1918-; Hammaker, Wilbur Emery, 1876-1968.; Morton, Thruston B. (Thruston Ballard), 1907-1982.; Munn, Earle Harold, 1903-; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Shaw, Mark Revell, 1889-
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Correspondence and other mailings 1951-2004
  - 1951-1958 undated (Box 1)
  - 1959 (Box 1)
  - 1960 (Box 1)
  - January-August 1961 (Box 1)
  - September-December 1961 (Box 1)
  - 1962 (Box 1)
  - 1963 (Box 1)
  - 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - 1967 (Box 1)
  - 1968 (Box 1)
  - 1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970 (Box 1)
  - 1971 (Box 1)
  - 1972 (Box 1)
  - 1973 (Box 1)
  - 1974 (Box 1)
  - 1975 (Box 1)
  - 1976 (Box 1)
  - 1986-2003 (Box 1)
  - 2004 (Box 1)
- Prohibition Party activities
  - National Prohibition Foundation miscellaneous 1953-1960 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Prohibition and Temperance Education Foundation (Box 1)
  - National Temperance and Prohibition Council (and related Prohibition Party) (Box 1)
  - Papers, including financial reports of the Prohibition Party National Committee and the National Convention 1955-1963 (Box 1)
  - Printed material, including assorted prohibition magazines and newsletters 1956-1963 (Box 1)
  - Papers concerning the Prohibition Party National Conference, Kansas City, Missouri 1966 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings concerning the Prohibition Party 1956-1966, undated (Box 1)
  - Printed materials, including campaign materials, pamphlets, etc. 1950-1964 (Box 1)
  - Papers; include Massachusetts election statistics 1948-1960 and national statistics, 1872-1960 (Box 2)
  - Papers concerning Dodge's campaign for the U.S. Senate from Kansas 1966 (Box 2)
  - Papers concerning dispute between Sam Morris and William Plymat 1951-1959 (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea concerning the Prohibition Party 1948-1961 (Box 2)
  - Letter from John A. Nicholls, state chairman of the Prohibition State Committee of Massachusetts to L.M. Aldrich 1906 (Box 2)
  - Notebook containing minutes of the Massachusetts Prohibition State Committee 1939-1962 (Box 2)
  - 1972 campaign materials (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook concerning the Prohibition Party and its candidates 1956-1959 (Box 2)
    (include photographs)
- Kalamazoo (Mich.) Activities
  - Greater Kalamazoo Council papers 1968-1969 (Box 2)
  - Kalamazoo Community Relations Board
    - 1967-1970, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - 1967-1970, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Kalamazoo School Board election and attempt to recall the Kalamazoo School Board 1969, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Kalamazoo schools -- sensitivity training 1969 (Box 3)
  - Dodge's campaign for the Kalamazoo City Commission 1969, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Kalamazoo Good Government Association
    - Papers 1968-1972, 7 folders (Box 3)
    - By-laws and form letters (Box 3)
    - Financial records (Box 3)
    - Newspaper clippings concerning the Michigan Civil Rights Commission and the Kalamazoo Good Government Association 1969 (Box 4)
    - Re the proposed city income tax (Box 4)
    - Re. the proposed housing commission, 2 folders (Box 4)
- Other Civic and Church activities
  - National Civic League, Inc. papers 1963-1964 (Box 4)
  - New Hope Baptist Church, Kansas City, Missouri Papers 1964-1965 (Box 4)
  - Australian Crusade Meetings papers 1966 National Christian Citizen Committee
    - Record book 1963 (Box 4)
    - 1961-1963, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1964-1966 (Box 4)
    - Incorporation and tax status papers 1963-1964 (Box 4)
    - Miscellanea 1962-1967 (Box 4)
  - Colorado State Elections Advisory Committee 1975, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings, speeches and other papers (Box 4)
- Visual Materials
  - Photograph of Prohibition Party (?) gathering (Box 4)
  - Photographs of International Reform Federation meetings, 3 photographs (Box 4)
  - Videotapes of Prohibition National Convention, 1987, 4 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 4)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Decker, Rutherford L.
1959, 1960, 1961, June 12, 1963
Gibbons, Delmar D., 1913-
Feb. 14, 1963, Feb. 22, 1963, Apr. 27, 1963, May 9, 1963, May 21, 1963, June 2, 1963, June 11, 1963, June 18, 1963, June 18, 1963, June 25, 1963, July 2, 1963, July 16, 1963, Sept. 3, 1963, June 18, 1966
Graham, Billy, 1918-
Dec. 21, 1959 [to Rev. R. Richard Staub]
Hammaker, Wilbur Emery, 1876-1968.
Apr. 16, 1957, Apr. 21, 1958, Aug. 25, 1959, Apr. 7, 1961, June 1, 1961, June 18, 1962, July 10, 1962, Jan. 11, 1963
Morton, Thruston B. (Thruston Ballard), 1907-1982.
Apr. 21, 1959, Apr. 27, 1959
Munn, Earle Harold, 1903-
July 3, 1959, Dec. 8, 1961, 1962, 1963
Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.
Sept. 27, 1960
Shaw, Mark Revell, 1889-
Oct. 9, 1954, Oct. 1957, Apr. 19, 1958, Apr. 23, 1958, 1962?, Apr. 11, 1962 [to Floyd G. Kitchen] May 21, 1962, May 29.1962, July 7, 1962, July 18, 1962 [to E. H. Munn]